Guide to the Bedford Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation oral histories 2008.030
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Keller, Thomas, 2008 February 9; 2008.030.21
  In this interview, Thomas Keller speaks with his colleague and friend, Wendell Rice. Keller recounts his early start with Restoration, which he joined in the year of its incorporation. Keller describes the thirty-year evolution of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, which was heavily influenced by Restoration's social, cultural, and economic interventions. Keller lists people he considers indispensable leaders in the founding and direction of Restoration and the Bedford-Stuyvesant community as a whole. At the interview's end, Keller envisions his hopes for the neighborhood's future, including increased home ownership, well-worn pathways to higher education -- including college and vocational training -- and support for young entrepreneurs. Interview conducted by Wendell Rice.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Billie Holiday Theatre; Keller, Thomas B.; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Knox, Elexux, 2008 May; 2008.030.22
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Knox, Elexux; Youth Arts Academy
- Lalanne, Martine, 2008 February 22; 2008.030.23
  Martine Lalanne is a resident of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. Her teenage daughter has danced with Restoration's Dance Theater Junior Company (part of Restoration's Youth Arts Academy) for over seven years.
  In this telephone interview, Martine Lalanne describes the impact Restoration's Dance Theater Junior Company has had on her daughter's life. She discusses the program's emphasis on community-building and positive role-modeling for children, and her hopes for its future. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; Girls |x Education (Secondary) |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Keller, Thomas B.; Lalanne, Martine; Youth Arts Academy
- Lanier, Elania, 2008 May; 2008.030.24
  Introduced to Restoration at age twelve, Elania Lanier's involvement with Restoration began in the 1980s. At the time of the 2008 interview, Lanier had recently received her master's degree in social work and juggled her new career with volunteer work at Restoration. She was also raising her teenage daughter, Kourtney Charles, who danced with the Youth Arts Academy's Dance Theater Junior Company. Additionally for Restoration, Lanier volunteered with the annual Kwanzaa celebrations and the annual Robert F. Kennedy party, and was the lead volunteer for the Dance Africa program.
  In this interview, Elania Lanier describes her connection to Restoration, as well as changes she's observed both at Restoration and with the community in the greater Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She discusses the positive impact Restoration's Youth Arts Academy (YAA) has had on her daughter, Kourtney Charles, and the YAA as a holistic support network for both youth and their parents. She compares Restoration with other cultural institutions. Lanier relates her fears for gentrification and displacement in Bedford-Stuyvesant. Interview conducted by Peggy Alston.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Dancers |z New York (State) |z New York; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Performing arts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation. Center for Art and Culture; Billie Holiday Theatre; Fiorello H. LaGuardia High School of Music and Art and Performing Arts (New York, N.Y.); Lanier, Elania; Youth Arts Academy
- Latif, Wadiya, 2008 January 7; 2008.030.25
  Wadiya Latif was born in 1947 in Brooklyn, New York. She grew up in the Crown Heights and Flatbush neighborhoods of Brooklyn, where she worshipped at the Presbyterian church, and attended P.S. 167, Walt Whitman Junior High, and Erasmus Hall High School. Both of Latif's parents were school teachers; her father rose to serve as the superintendent after whom Brooklyn's Walter Weaver Elementary School (P.S. 398) was named. Latif attended the historically Black Hampton University (also her mother's alma mater). As an adult Latif became employed at Restoration in January 1971, when its headquarters were still located at the Hotel Grenada. At the time of the interview, Latif worked as Restoration's commercial leasing manager with responsibility for Restoration Plaza.
  In this interview, Wadiya Latif, a long-time employee of Restoration, shares memories from Restoration's earliest years. She remembers the Home Improvement Program and the mortgage pool, officially named the Restoration Funding Corporation. Latif recalls Restoration's loss of funding from the Special Impact Program, and describes the organization's evolving goals as it navigated a new reality of reduced federal funding, including a period of layoffs. Latif recounts the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn's culture circa 1971, an accidental shooting that left her son paralyzed, her conversion to Sunni Islam, and discusses the lives of her three children. At the interview's end, Latif reflects on the importance of voting and healthy political leaders, particularly at the highest levels of government. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Activism; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Conversion |x Islam; Fundraising |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Presidents |z United States |x Election |y 2008; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Hampton University (Va.); Latif, Wadiyah
- Lewis, Stuart, 2008 January 30; 2008.030.26
  Dr. Stuart Lewis was born in Jamaica and immigrated to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn in 1961, when he was a young boy. In 1974 he graduated from Harvard Medical School. Dr. Lewis practiced surgery in Brooklyn before becoming the Medical Director for the New York City Transit Authority, where he served for thirteen years. At the time of the interview, Dr. Lewis held a private practice. Prior to starting medical school, Dr. Lewis helped found Youth in Action, a youth anti-poverty organization. From 1966 to 1969 he was the Director of the Neighborhood Youth Corps, a component of Youth in Action. A longstanding community organizer and philanthropist, he served as the Chairman of the Board of Restoration from 1997 to 2000.
  In this interview, Dr. Stuart Lewis describes his personal activist mission, his interest in capital formation and the eradication of poverty, the economic state of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood and greater Brooklyn, and his time with Youth in Action in the 1960s. He discusses the initial division in duties between Restoration and the Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation, and reviews why his last act as Chairman merged the two divisions. He tells the history of Weeksville and its discovery. Lewis recounts the African American contributions to a diverse community and states the role of arts and culture in society. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Youth in Action; Inniss, Charles E.; Lewis, Stuart, Dr.; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History
- London, Ashley, 2008 May; 2008.030.27
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; London, Ashley; Youth Arts Academy
- Long, Hardy Joe, 2008 May 13; 2008.030.28
  Hardy Joe Long, a longtime businessman and community pillar of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, was the owner of the Burdell's store (which he'd purchased in 1968), and served as president of the Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association.
  In this interview, the businessman Hardy Joe Long recounts his role in the community of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn as a merchant and active participant in the Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association. He enumerates different changes he's seen in the community over the past over fifty years, including racial mixing, economic development, and a cultural renaissance. Long lists different contributions heralded by Restoration, including support for small businesses via the backing of the Merchants Association. He tells of an impoverished childhood in North Carolina, and the ambition that drove him to own a business in New York City -- a dream that was enabled by Restoration's revolving loan fund. At the interview's end, Long details the Merchants Association's campaign to establish the Bedford-Stuyvesant Gateway Business Improvement District. Interview conducted by Bernadette Mitchell.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Grannum, Colvin W.; Long, Hardy Joe
- McRae, Bernice, 2008 April 11; 2008.030.29
  Bernice McCrae grew up in Georgia and moved to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn as a young adult. She was a long-time employee of Restoration. At the time of the 2008 interview, she had worked there for thirty years, and held the position of director of small business services, where she worked in consulting would-be local entrepreneurs about business ownership, and mentored them through the loan application process for the Restoration revolving loan fund.
  In this interview, Bernice McCrae recalls her start at Restoration and subsequent move to the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. A Restoration employee for over thirty years, McCrae says Restoration is the only true employer she's ever had. McCrae describes three decades of the neighborhood's evolution; much of it greatly influenced by the social, cultural, and economic interventions spearheaded by Restoration. In great detail, she discusses her position in Restoration's small business loan foundation, capital fund, and entrepreneurship education. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Discrimination in mortgage loans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; McRae, Bernice
- Mitchell, Roderick, 2008 January 28; 2008.030.30
  Roderick "Rocky" Mitchell grew up in Yanceyville, North Carolina. He earned a bachelor's degree in economics from the University of California, Los Angeles in 1977 and a master's degree in business administration from Columbia University in 1981. Mitchell joined Restoration as controller, then served as vice president of physical development. At thirty-two years old, Mitchell took helm of the presidency in 1988, after an era of budget cuts spearheaded by United States President Ronald Reagan left the community development corporation on the verge of insolvency. Mitchell resigned from the presidency of Restoration in 2000, after public criticism and news coverage in papers such as The New York Times. Mitchell served as president for twelve years; as of 2008 that was the longest presidential tenure in Restoration's history.
  In this interview, Roderick "Rocky" Mitchell provides his brief biography, and details his introduction to Restoration. Mitchell spends a portion of the interview praising and thanking colleagues, board members, and financial donors who were influential in his tenure's successes. Mitchell alleges that his presidency's great achievement was its transition from being largely government supported to being mostly independently funded. He says the era of traditional community development corporations, which survive by "government largesse" have died, and proposes the necessity that such non-profits be run with the ethos and discipline of for-profit companies. Mitchell touches on other accomplishments, including profitable ventures with Pathmark, which funded a donation to the Weeksville Heritage Center. Interview conducted by Clarence Stewart with Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Economic conditions |y 21st century; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nonprofit organizations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Mitchell, Roderick; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History
- Pei, I.M., 2008 February 22; 2008.030.31
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Pei, I. M.
- Pickman, James, 2008 January 14; 2008.030.32
  James Pickman, born 1942, served as general counsel to Restoration in its early years, from 1972 to 1977. Pickman grew up in Queens County, New York and Long Island, New York; after law school, he returned to New York City. Pickman and his wife Elizabeth founded the James and Elizabeth Pickman Foundation, which they used as an outlet for philanthropic giving to Restoration in the decades after Pickman's departure from Restoration. The Pickmans were also active in the Restoration alumni association.
  In this telephone interview, James Pickman describes his path to serving as Restoration's general counsel during its early years, from 1972 to 1977. Pickman provides brief biographical notes, including on his schooling and early career. He discusses the physical and political climate of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn circa 1972, remembering an area in need of physical rejuvenation, employment opportunities, entrepreneurial incubation, and the repeal of government and business policies that oppressed many of Bedford-Stuvyesant's residents – including redlining. Pickman candidly recalls a segregated and paternalistic relationship between Restoration and its early twin corporation, the Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation. He describes the nature of Board work at Restoration, including cultivating alliances with corporate, lending, and government institutions; and reflects on Restoration's legacy and influence on future community development corporations. Interview conducted by Sady Sullivan.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Politics and government; Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Philanthropists |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Segregation |z United States; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Doar, John; Pickman, James; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Ramnauth, David, 2008 May 13; 2008.030.33
  David Ramnauth was the owner of Big Brother's Discount Hardware and Appliance. After immigrating to America in 1975 from the small village of Leguan, Guyana, Ramnauth grew up in Brooklyn and attended P.S. 93.
  In this interview, David Ramnauth discusses his motivation for starting a business; he says the family's entrepreneurial spirit began in their hometown of Leguan, Guyana, where his mother started a donkey-cart vending venture. Ramnauth says that in America, the Ramnauths turned to licensed street vending to subsidize the high cost of living; but by saving their money, they eventually purchased Big Brother's Discount Hardware and Appliance. Ramnauth discusses the pros and cons of merchants' associations, business improvement districts, and gentrification. Ramnauth tells of his philanthropic philosophy, and reflects on the decline of the American small business. Interview conducted by Bahati Williams.
  Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Business enterprises |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Enterprise zones |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Entrepreneurship |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Gentrification |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Dabu, Joel; Fulton-Nostrand United Merchants Association; Ramnauth, David
- Rice, Wendell, 2007 August 31; 2008.030.34
  Wendell Rice was born in 1943 in Conway, South Carolina, and moved to Brooklyn, New York City after graduating high school in 1961. While Rice's initial ambition was to operate bulldozers, he was stymied by racial discrimination. After a number of odd jobs led to disappointment and Rice was the victim of an armed robbery, he became involved with Restoration's community organizer training program. Rice's career was spent with Restoration, and he saw many of its hallmark programs come to fruition, including rezoned superblocks, programs in youth enrichment, and the Weatherization Assistance Program of which Rice served as director. Rice holds a bachelor's degree in sociology and political science from Brooklyn College. He has two adult children.
  In this interview, Wendell Rice describes his early career, including experiences with racial discrimination within city employment in the 1960s; and his path to employment with Restoration. He recalls prime moments in his career as a community organizer, including his essential involvement with the superblocks program to rezone urban residential streets. He details work as a youth organizer, including the removal of heroin addicts from neighborhood streets, and the education of children at risk of gang affiliation. Near the interview's end, Rice explains the Weatherization Assistance Program, including its mission, customers, day-to-day operations, and technology-centric future. Interview conducted by Brian Purnell.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Community development corporations |z New York (State) |z New York; Community development, Urban |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Economic development |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Housing |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Inniss, Charles E.; Keller, Thomas B.; Rice, Wendell; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Richardson, Elsie, 2008 January 22; 2008.030.35
  Elsie Richardson was born in Manhattan in 1922 and grew up in the East Harlem neighborhood known as "El Barrio." Richardson moved to Brooklyn in 1946, around the time of her wedding, and lived with her family in the Albany Projects before settling in a long-term home on Prospect Place. A public school secretary by day, Richardson was otherwise an engaged community leader who co-founded the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (CBCC) and was essential in the creation of the nation's first non-profit community development corporation, Restoration. In February 1966, Richardson led Senators Robert F. Kennedy and Jacob Javits on the famous tour of the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn, which resulted in the formation of Restoration. Richardson held a bachelor's degree from Pratt Institute and a master's degree from the New School for Social Research. She had three children. Elsie Richardson died in Brooklyn in 2012.
  In part one of the interview, Elsie Richardson discusses the founding of the Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (CBCC) in the Bedford-Stuyvesant neighborhood of Brooklyn. She recalls the 1966 walking tour of Bedford-Stuyvesant with Senators Kennedy and Javits, a key event in the formation of Restoration. She remembers Restoration's early years, including the initial cleavage between Restoration and the Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation. Richardson reminisces about the archaeological discovery of the town of Weeksville, a post-slavery African American settlement in Brooklyn. She offers thoughts on today's school system and youth culture, as well as life in Brooklyn circa the 1960s. Richardson's granddaughter and great grandson join the conversation in later moments. The last few minutes comprise part two, conducted via telephone. Richardson shares behind-the-scenes classism and sexism at the time of Restoration's founding. Interview conducted by Deborah Jones with Sady Sullivan.
  African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Civil rights movements |z United States |y 20th century; Community centers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Urban renewal |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bedford-Stuyvesant Development and Services Corporation; Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation; Central Brooklyn Coordinating Council (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Kennedy, Robert F.; Richardson, Elsie; Rose, Lucille; Society for the Preservation of Weeksville and Bedford-Stuyvesant History; Thomas, Franklin A.
- Robinson, Annette, 2008 February 1; 2008.030.36